Guide to the Hans Horst Meyer papers, 1800s-1939, 2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hans Horst Meyer papers 1800s-1939, 2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Meyer, Hans Horst, 1853-1939
6.7 linear feet Extent: Approx. 147 Items
Hans Horst Meyer was a German pharmacologist (1853-1939) and professor at the Vienna Medical School, 1904-1924. The Hans Horst Meyer papers comprise a small amount of personal and professional correspondence; genealogical documents; diplomas, honors, medals, and awards received by Meyer between 1901 and 1937; a series of photographs of Meyer, his family members, and Harvey Cushing; and an autograph album with signatures and correspondence of notable individuals. The certificates and medals come from a variety of international scientific organizations, such as the New York Academy of Medicine, the Royal Society of Physicians in Budapest, and the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences. Meyer also received the German Order of the Red Eagle and honorary citizenship of the city of Vienna. Also included are some correspondence and printed materials relating to the honors received by Meyer, as well as a reprint of Meyer's chapter in the Handbuch der experimentellen Pharmakologie. The majority of the materials was acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
RL.00894
Language: Material in German, English, Latin, Spanish, and Italian
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Hans Horst Meyer papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1998 and as a transfer in 2011.
Biographical Note
Hans Horst Meyer holds a prominent place at the historical intersection of pharmacology and anesthesia. His greatest achievement was in the formulation of the lipoid theory of narcosis which still stands today largely unchallenged. Published in 1899, Meyer's classic paper proposed that the ability of a substance to produce narcosis or anesthesia is governed by its partition coefficient. He shares the honor as the cofounder of this theory with Charles Overton who independently arrived at the same conclusion at the same time although indirectly through a study of permeability of plant and animal cells to various substances. The Meyer-Overton theory stimulated decades of research to answer important questions of exactly how certain drugs can act to produce a state of anesthesia. [Taken from Trent Associates Report 12, no. 1 (Spring/Summer 2004): 1-2]
Meyer was born in Insterburg, East Prussia (now part of Russia), and studied medicine in Königsberg, Leipzig, and Berlin. He held the chair of pharmacology at the University of Marburg from 1884 to 1904, and was then professor at the Vienna Medical School from 1904 to 1924, when he retired. Meyer died in Vienna in October, 1939.
Meyer had three sons, Kurt Heinrich, Arthur Woldemar, and Friedrich Horst, who died as a child. In 1933, Meyer's middle son Arthur shot his wife then committed suicide, following the family's persecution due to his wife's Jewish background. Arthur Meyer's son, J. Horst Meyer, was a professor of physics at Duke University from 1959 to 2004. [Source: Wikipedia, June 2014.]
Collection Overview
The Hans Horst Meyer papers contain personal and professional correspondence; genealogical documents; diplomas, honors, medals, and awards received by Meyer between 1901 and 1937; a series of photographs of Meyer, his family members, and Harvey Cushing; and an autograph album with signatures and correspondence of notable individuals. The certificates and medals come from a variety of international scientific organizations, such as the New York Academy of Medicine, the Royal Society of Physicians in Budapest, and the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences. Meyer also received the German Order of the Red Eagle and honorary citizenship of the city of Vienna. Also included are some correspondence and printed materials relating to the honors received by Meyer, as well as a reprint of Meyer's chapter in the Handbuch der experimentellen Pharmakologie.
An addition of personal papers reveals Meyer's efforts while he was living in Vienna to document his family's history, and includes official documents, an identity card, and personal correspondence from the last decades of his life, some dating from the last year of his life, 1939. There are also a few photographs in this addition. Almost all the documents in this addition are in German.
The autograph album contains 147 autographs and letters of well-known and lesser-known Germans, most of whom lived in the 19th century. Included are a letter each from Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, Johann Christoph Friedrich von Schiller, and Clara Schumann, a postcard from Johannes Brahms, and the autographs of many individuals, including, Henrik Ibsen and Charles Dickens.
With the exception of the scrapbook, which was originally in the holdings of the Rubenstein Library general collections, the materials were acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Meyer, Hans Horst, 1853-1939; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Autographs -- Germany -- 19th century; Pharmacology -- Germany -- History -- 20th century; Vienna (Austria) -- History; Vienna (Austria) -- Intellectual life; Photographs; Autograph albums; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Photographs Series, 1914-1935, 2004 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Black-and-white photographs of Meyer in Vienna and Berlin and of Meyer's family and colleagues, including two signed photographs of Harvey Cushing. Also includes a photograph of the presentation of a portrait of Meyer to Duke University by his grandson, J. Horst Meyer, circa 2004. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Meyer with hat; Meyer at a very early age; Meyer and his sons, Arthur W. and Kurt H., in World War I uniform, 1914 (Box 1)
  - Harvey Cushing, autographed to Meyer, 1914 (Box 2)
  - Meyer and associates, Vienna, July 1924 (Box 1)
  - Harvey Cushing, autographed to Meyer, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Meyer with daughter-in-law, Lotte Meyer, and grandson, Horst Meyer, in Berlin; Meyer with grandson, Horst Meyer, in Vienna, 1931; Meyer with grandson, Horst Meyer, in Vienna, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Presentation by J. Horst Meyer of portrait of Hans Horst Meyer [by Rietti, 1911] to Duke University, circa 2004 (Box 2)
  - Harvey Cushing; hand-drawn sketch of spongioblast; Meyer, undated (Box 1)
  - Early photograph of Meyer and associates in Vienna, undated (Box 1)
  - Meyer at his desk, undated (Box 2)
  - Portrait photograph of Meyer, undated (Box 2)
  - Meyer at his desk in Vienna, undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia Series, 1901-1937 and undated, (5 boxes) (Box 2)
  Diplomas, certificates, and medals conferring honorary membership and other honors on Meyer from a variety of international scientific organizations and institutes. Completing the series is an autograph album containing 147 autographs and letters of well-known and lesser-known Germans, most of whom lived in the 19th century. Included are a letter each from Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, Johann Christoph Friedrich von Schiller, and Clara Schumann, a postcard from Johannes Brahms, and the autographs of many individuals, including, Henrik Ibsen and Charles Dickens. Subgroupings are arranged in chronological order.
  - Diplomas and Certificates (Box 2)
    - Rothen Adler-Orden vierter Klasse, 1901 (Box 3)
    - Royal Society of Physicians, Budapest, 1905 (Box 3)
    - Physikalisch-medizinische Sozietät zu Erlangen, 1908 (Box 4)
    - Kaiserliche Leopoldinische-Carolinische Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher, 1911 (Box 4)
    - University of St. Andrews, 1913 (Box 4)
    - Gesellschaft der Aertze in Wien, 1923 (Box 4)
    - Accademia Medico-Fisica Fiorentina, 1924 (Box 4)
    - Kaiserliche Deutsche Academie der Naturforscher zu Halle, 1925 (Box 4)
    - Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences, 1931 (Box 4)
    - Honorary Citizenship, City of Vienna, 1932 (Box 5)
    - Verein für Psychiatrie und Neurologie in Wien, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Deutsche Pharmakologische Gesellschaft, 1933 (Box 3)
    - Akademie der Wissenschaftern, 1933 (Box 5)
    - La Academia Nacional de Medicina, 1934 (Box 4)
    - New York Academy of Medicine, 1936 (Box 3)
    - University of Vienna, Professor Emeritus of Pharmacology, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Medals (Box 5)
    - Royal Order of the Vasa, Sweden, late 19th century (Box 6)
    - Commemorative bronze medal in honor of Prof. Hans Horst Meyer's 70th Birthday, Austrian Academy of Sciences, 1923 (Box 6)
    - Minerva Medal awarded by the Kaiser Wilhelm Society for the Advancement of Science (Box 6)
  - Autograph book, 1800s (Box 7)
- Papers Series, 1905-1935, (2 boxes) (Box 7)
  Correspondence and printed material relating to the honors received by Meyer, as well as a reprint of Meyer's chapter in the Handbuch der experimentellen Pharmakologie. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Kaiserliche Akademie der Wissenschaften in Wien, 1905 (Box 3)
  - University of St. Andrews, 1913 (Box 3)
  - Kaiserliche Deutsche Academie der Naturforscher zu Halle, 1925 (Box 3)
  - Letter to Dr. Arthur Meyer from Harvey Cushing, 1928, Feb. 17 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Meyer from J.A. Gunn, British Pharmacologic Society, Oxford, England, 1931, Aug. 7 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Meyer from H. Mackeith, Oxford, England, 1932, Sept. 12 (Box 1)
  - Verein für Psychiatrie und Neurologie in Wien, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Academia Nacional de Medicina, 1935 (Box 3)
  - Hans Horst Meyer, Wesen und Sinn der experimentellen Pharmakologie, Handbuch der experimentellen Pharmakologie, edited by W. Heubner and J. Schüller, Bd. 1 (Berlin: Springer Verlag, 1935), 1-10. (Box 2)
- Addition, 2013-0146, 1869-1939 and undated, (1 box) (Box 2)
  Addition to the Hans Horst Meyers papers of about 100 items relates to Hans Horst Meyer's search for his family's origins in light of events unfolding in Nazi Germany. At the time, he was living in Vienna. Papers consist of genealogical documents listing his parents and grandparents and their religious status; correspondence from the 1930s; official documents pertaining to Meyer's own status and perhaps travel intentions; and papers and a certificate from St. Andrews in Edinburgh. Addition also includes a series of small photographs - head shots of Meyer (possibly taken for travel documents), and an undated carte-de-visite of Meyer and probably his wife, Doris, dating most likely to the 1890s. Almost all the documents are in German. Each folder is arranged in roughly chronological order.
  - Addition (2013-0146) (Box 7)